Hello and welcome back, I want to talk now about a half transform.
大家好 欢迎回来 今天我们学习霍夫变换 (Hough Transform)
The half transform is a really nice technique to detect objects, to segment
霍夫变换是一种很强的技术 可以用来检测和分割对象
out objects, for which you know their shape.
尤其是对于你已知形状的物体
Maybe a straight line, maybe a circle, as we have seen in the previous example.
正如我们在前面例子里看到的 它也许是直线或者圆
For example we want to detect the ball. We know it's circular.
比如我们要检测一个球 我们知道它是圆形的
So can we include that information in our detection, in our segmentation technique,
所以在我们的检测和分割技术中 是否能包含这条信息
to detect that it's actually circular? Can we use the information that we're
来检测圆形的对象？  我们能将检测对象是直线这条信息用上
expecting here as a straight line, and basically get a straight line.
来最终检测到一条直线吗？
So the half transform allows to do that, and in a very simple and really, really
霍夫变换可以做到 它的方法非常简单也非常漂亮
nice fashion. Let's illustrate that.
让我来演示一下
The basic idea is quite simple, and we're going to start with ideas on how to
基本思路相当简单 我将从检测直线开始讲解
detect straight lines, and then we're going to move to circles.
然后讲解如何检测圆形
But starting with straight lines makes it much, much easier to understand.
但从直线讲起会更加容易理解
In school I mean, probably in elementary or middle school you have learned how to
在学校里 也许是小学或者中学 你已经学习了
represent a straight line that is on a plane.
如何在平面上表示一条直线
And I'm going to write down the equations and explain them to you again.
我会写下方程 并给你再讲解一下
So here we have the plane. This is a image plane, the x y.
这儿有一个平面 它是一个图像平面 这是x y 轴
This is the image plane and we have points on a straight line on the plane.
平面上的直线上有许多点
For example this straight line might be this one or this one.
比如直线可以是这条 或者这条
Now a straight line on a plane is represented, can be written down in the
这儿表示平面上的一条直线 它能用如下的形式写出来
following form. We have rho, and I'm going to explain
我们有 ρ 过一会再解释这些符号
each one of these symbols in a second, is X cosine theta plus Y sine theta.
ρ 等于 x cosθ 加上 y sinθ
So rho is the distance from the coordinate system's center to the
ρ 是坐标系统的原点到这条直线的距离
straight line, and this should be perpendicular, of course.
这儿应该是垂直的
It's a distance. Might be a bit tilted in the video, but
它表示距离 视频里有点斜
it should be, basically, a 90 degrees angle.
但无论如何 它应该是一个90度的直角
So rho is the distance to the straight line, and theta is this angle here that
ρ 是原点到直线的距离 而 θ 是这儿的一个角
basically is the angle with one of the axes. Let's pick this one in this case
是距离和某一条坐标轴所夹的角
with the line connecting test center with the straight line that we are
这儿我们取 x轴和原点到直线的距离所夹的角表示 θ
considering. So basically, every point that is on the
直线上的每一点都满足这个方程
line holds this equation. Every single point, this one and this one
每一个单独的点 比如这点和这点
and every point in the line will hold this equation.
这条直线上所有点都将满足此方程
Using that, here is the idea of the half transform.
利用这个方程 这儿是霍夫变换的原理
We take a point on the image and that comes from the edge detection.
选取图像上经过边缘检测得到的一点
So basically every point that the edge detector said, there is an edge going
对于由边缘检测所得到的每个点 都有一条边线经过它
through. For every point, we basically have an
对于每个点
infinite number of lines going through it.
有无穷条直线可以经过它
This is one of them, with a particular rho and a particular theta.
这是其中的一条直线 对应特定的 ρ 和 θ
Now, let's draw a different one. This line has its own rho and its own
让我们画条不同的直线 这条直线也有特定的 ρ 和 θ
theta. This will be rho, this will be theta.
这儿代表ρ 这儿代表θ
We can go and draw a different line, all the lines going through the point.
还可以画条不同的直线 所有的直线经过这个点
See, here is another one. It has its own rho, here, and its own
看这儿又是一条直线 它也有相应的 ρ 和 θ
theta. And we can keep doing that, we can pick
我们可以一直这样画下去
yet another one. For example, let us pick this one.
比如 这儿再画一条
And, he had rope. And it has theta.
它也有相应的 ρ 和 θ
So, every point has an infinite number of lines.
所以每个点都有无穷多条直线经过它
And basically, every point will go and say, any of those lines is okay with me.
也能说这些直线对这样的点都是满足要求的
The point will go and vote for. Ro.
这个点将对应一系列的 ( ρ , θ )
And theta for a series of them. It should be voting for an infinite
它应该对应于无穷多个对
number but we're going to discrotize we're going to do this on the computer so
但我们将进行离散化 因为用计算机操作
we won't be able to vote for an infinite number.
所以我们不会取无穷多的值
We're going to vote for discreet space of row and feta.
我们将映射出一个离散的 ρθ空间
Now that's only one point and basically every possible line that goes through
这是一点 每条经过它的直线
that point will get one vote. Okay.
都与它对应 好了
Now what happens with this other point? This other point has it's own lines that
对于另外一点呢？ 另外一点也有许多直线相交于它
go through it. So it's going to go and vote for it's own
所以它也有对应它的直线
lines. It's going to vote for this one of
当然包括这条也与它对应
course. But it's also going to vote, for example,
但它同时也会与这一条对应
for this one. That has its own rho and its own theta.
这条直线有自己的ρ和θ
And it's going to vote, and I don't want to draw too many, because it will make
我不想画太多的直线 因为多了会看不清楚
the picture very unclear. But it's going to vote for another line
但它的确还对应于这儿的一条直线 还有这儿的 等等
here and another line here and so on. So it's basically going to vote also for
所以这点也对应了一系列的  ( ρ , θ )
a series of rho and theta. And all the votes will get one vote.
所有这些直线都会与一个点对应
But look what happened. This line is common to both of them.
这条直线同时经过两点
And we know that in Euclidean space through two points, there is a single
我们知道欧式空间中两点确定一条直线
line. So there is only one line.
所以这样的直线只有一条
The one that we are looking for, that's going to get two votes.
我们需要检测的这条直线与两个有效点对应
Basically, and that will help us to understand what's the row and the theta
这将有助于知道这条直线的ρ和θ
for this line. But of course not only two vaults,
当然不仅仅只有两个有效点
because there's going to be another point here, that's also going to vote for a
因为这儿还有另外一点 它也对应一组ρ和θ
series of rho and theta, but is going to vote for this one.
这点也投票给这条直线
So this one is now getting three votes, one for each point that the edge detector
所以这条直线现在对应有3个有效点 由边缘检测出的这些点
found, that is on that line.
都在那条直线上
now of course the edge detector might find points that are outside of that
当然边缘检测也许会找到那条直线之外的点
line, and those will also make their own votes, but hopefully the only line that
它们也会进行投票 但幸运的是
gets a large number of votes is the line of interest.
只有对应最多有效点的直线才是我们感兴趣的直线
So that's the basic idea of the Hough transform, and we're going to provide
这就是霍夫变换的基本原理 过一会我将进一步讲解
more details in a second but every point that the edge detector find votes for the
但边缘检测器找到的每个点会使对应直线增加确定性
possibilities, in this case, lines. If we have multiple points on the same
如果在一条直线上有许多这样的点
line, then we're going to have multiple votes.
那么这条线就会得到很多投票
So how do we do that in reality. So, in reality, we are going to go from
在实际中我们是如何做的呢 我们会建立XY坐标系统
the XY coordinate system, which means the image coordinate system, to a new
也就是图像的坐标系
coordinate system, which is theta and rho.
再映射到一个新的坐标系 即 ρθ 坐标系
That coordinate the system, the same way that our image is discretized,
这个新的坐标系和图像的坐标系一样 都是离散的
is going to be discretized. So theta can be anything around the
它们将被离散化 围绕圆周 θ 可以是任何值
circle, and we basically discrotize as fine as we want or as fine as our memory
离散化程度 取决于我们的需要或者内存大小
or our, our computational time allow us. Let's say we can discretize every one
或者计算时间的限制 比如 我们精确到一度
degree. We do the same for rho, we discrotize it.
同样地 我们对 ρ 进行离散化
We know that row can not go further than the size of the image, so we know it's
我们知道 ρ 的长度不能超过图像的尺寸 所以它是有界的
bounded, and then we basically discretize it.
然后我们可以对它进行离散化
And then what we're going to do, let me write the equation again, with half the
接下来要进行的 我先再次写下这个方程
equation, rho x, cosine theta plus y sine theta.
ρ 等于 xcosθ 加上 ysinθ
So what we are going to do is the following.
那么接下来我要做的是
We go through every point, let's say this one.
我们遍历每个点 比如这个点
So every point gives us x, y, the coordinates of that point.
每点都对应 (x,y) 也就是这点的坐标
Then we run through theta, and we say, let's say, one degree.
然后我们遍历 θ 值 比如某个角度
So we have the coordinate x and y. We put cosine of one, sine of one.
我们有坐标 (x,y)  我们有 cosθ sinθ
That gives us a rho. We go and vote for that one.
得到一个 ρ 在 ρθ 空间我们就投出一票给它
We, let's say, add one vote. This is sometimes called the accumulator.
我们说得到一票 有时也叫累加器
And then we go ascertain, theta now equal two.
然后计算下一个 现在  θ 等于2
We have x, y. We define theta 2.
我们知道 x y 固定 θ 等于2
We have cosine of two plus sine of two. We get a new rho.
求出 cos2 和 sin2 我们得到一个新的 ρ
We go and vote for that one as well. And we keep voting for every single
我们投一票给它 继续为所有其他点投票
point. Now it's not very hard to see that once
现在不难看出 一旦确定了 x 和 y
you fix x and y, if you vary theta as here, or as here, rho changes in a
如果你改变这儿的 θ 值 则 ρ 会以正弦形式跟着变化
sinusoidal fashion. So, that's very easy and it counts on the
这非常容易理解 因为它依赖 cos 和 sin
cosine and sine. So your votes will look like a sinusoidal
对于每个点 你投票的离散点构成一条正弦曲线
function for every single point. Remember now when I go to a second point,
记住 现在当我移动到第二点时
I will got, I will get more votes, a different sinusoidal.
我将得到更多的投票 一条不同的正弦曲线
So I will get different votes, and there will be a place, the place for responding
所以我得到了不同的投票曲线 这将有一个交点
to this straight line, that is starting to accumulate votes.
这个交点就表示这条直线 我们开始累加投票了
Everything, for every point, we are going to have
对应每个点 我们有一条正弦曲线
that sinusoidal. We vote basically, on that sinusoidal,
我们对正弦曲线上的离散点进行投票
and we start to accumulate. And now, the next step is to go into the
我们开始累加 下一步我们研究累加计数
accumulator, and find the maxima. It may be multiple, if there are multiple
选出峰值 如果有多条直线 就会有多个峰值
straight lines, but we go and find, and say, oh,
我们寻找并发现
this is the rho and theta that many points like,
许多点都对应这对 ( ρ , θ )
and that's how we detect these lines. So, let me just run you through the
这就是检测直线的方法 让我们再来看下饼图直线
pipeline again. You start from the image, and you do an
你首先得到这副图像
edge detection. Every point.
然后你做边缘检测 得到每个点
Some of them in the lines that you care about.
其中一些点在你感兴趣的直线上
Some of them outside. Every point defines an equation like
一些点在外面 每个点确定这样一个方程
this. Every point gives you the x, y
每个点都有一个坐标 (x,y)
coordinates. So you go into the accumulator space, and
接着你研究累加数组空间
you vote sinusoidal votes. Or you just run through the thetas in the
你对正弦曲线进行投票 或者在离散空间遍历 θ
discretized space and you vote for every rho that you get from this equation.
通过这个方程得到对应的 ρ 对它进行投票
Every point a vote, then you finish, you basically say, lets go and look which
每个点对应一条曲线  当你做完这些
areas, which basically entries in my accumulator have enough bolts that means
你看看累加数组中的哪些值比较大
that there is a straight line going through them.
那就意味着图像中有一条直线
Now this concept of voting goes very far, and you can actually do many, many things
关于投票的概念我们已经讲了很多了 你现在能做许多事了
beyond detecting straight lines. Let us show one example.
除了识别直线之外 我们来看一个例子
The basic, so here, we have four, five points, and then they accumulators so its
这里有4 5个点 这是累加器
just going and you will see there is a straight line so there will be three
这里有条直线 这条线应该有三票
votes for that, and there is another straight line that will should be three
这里还有一条直线 也应该有三票
votes. Two votes, two votes, and so on.
这条线有两票 这也是两票 等等
For this very, very particular example, I just want to use it to show how we
使用这个具体的例子是想说明
basically get this sinusoidal type of votes for every point.
直线上的每个点所对应的正弦曲线是如何得到的
Now, let's see that on a real image. So what we see here is an aerial image
现在 我们实图演练一番 这是一张航拍地图
here. we clearly see that there is some
能够很清楚地看到有一些直线
straight lines. This is the result of edge detection.
这是边缘识别的结果
In particular, it's a canny edge detector.
更精确地说 这是一个Canny边缘检测器
Now, it's a bit confusing. From it, we want to get the parametrized
从这个图片上 我们想得到一条用参数表示的直线
straight line. We want to go the rho, we want to get the
我们想得到这条线的 ρ 和 θ
rho and theta for this one. This is the picture of this accumulator
ρ 和 θ 这是穿过了所有这些点的累加器
that went through all these points. Now, you don't need to use all of them.
你没有必要使用直线上所有的点
You can just sample some of them. There's plenty of points on this straight
从直线上抽样的选取几个点就可以了 直线上有许多的点
line so you will get very high accumulator just by using a subset of
仅仅使用这些点中的一个子集就能得到很高的累加值
them. But, this is the result of the
这里是累加器的结果
accumulator. And then you go here and you look for the
然后 在平面上找
maximum values. And from then you get the rho and the
最大值 并在平面内找到与最大值对应的
theta that correspond to those maximum values.
ρ 和 θ
Remember this is your theta, rho accumulator.
记住这是以ρ 和 θ为坐标系的累加器
So wherever is the maximum, it gives you a value for theta and a value for rho,
在得到最大值的同时 也能得到相应的ρ 和 θ的值
and those corresponds to what we see here, and then you can put it back on the
这与我们在这看到的相对应 然后可以把它放回到图像中
picture and say, this is my most basically extreme line, my most prominent
我们可以认为 基本上这就是最直的线 能得到的最显著的线
line. Then there might be other maximal.
可能会有另外的最值
There would certainly be for this line, and this line, and this, and you can go
像这条 这条 和这条线肯定都有相应的最值与其对应
and pick all of them. In this case, we are only marking the
可以把它们全找出来 在这个例子中 我们仅仅标出了
most prominent one, a very simple and extremely powerful technique.
图像中最明显的一条线 这是个非常简单但是非常强大的技术
I want to show you also how we do this for circuits but before that I want to
还想向大家展示如何处理环形 但是在那之前
run this example in mat lab. Let's see that.
先用matlab展示下这个例子 我们一起来看下
We're now as we said inside the mat lab environment.
现在已经打开了matlab
And let's see the type of operations that we are going to do to illustrate the
让我们来看下演示霍夫(Hough)变换所要做的运算
Hough transform to the text trade lines. So there is a bunch of commands here but
这里有一些命令语句
I'm going to describe them to you. Most of them are just to make nice plot.
一会儿会为大家讲解 它们中的大多数只是为了作图好看
I'm going to describe to you those that are important, to understand what
我将只描述一些重要的
basically the Hough transform is doing here.
hough 变换的基本用法
So first, as we have seen many times in the past, we read the image.
第一步 和以前一样 先载入图像文件
This is the first operation. Then we're going to rotate that image.
这是第一步 接下来 旋转图像
This is just for the fun of it. I don't want you to believe that we can
这只是为了增强趣味 我不想让你们认为霍夫变换只能
only detect horizontal or vertical lines, so we're going to rotate that image.
识别水平线或垂直线 所以我们旋转图像
Here, we do edges. Remember, the first thing we need to do
然后识别边界 记住 第一件要做的事
is detect the edges in the image. That's the input to the Hough transform.
是识别出图像里的边界线 边界是霍夫变换的输入参数
And then here it is the Hough transform in MATLAB.
然后 这就是matlab里的hough 变换了
That would basically create this accumulator in the theta rho space.
这行命令用于生成ρ 和 θ空间的计数器
And these are a bunch of operations, just to illustrate, to visualize.
这些行运算是为了可视化
We're going to run it in a second, I'm just describing the operations for now.
现在只是简单描述下这些运算 接下来就运行程序
Then, the next, we need to detect the peaks.
下一步 我们需要识别出计数器的峰值
We need to detect the maximal in the accumulator.
需要识别出计数器中的最大值
And that's this operation, and we're going to plot it.
这个运算就是为了这个目的 我们将把峰值标出来
Now we have the maximal, which means that we have the rho, and the theta and, we
现在找到了最大值 也意味着找到了与之相对应的ρ 和 θ
need to detect the lines. We actually need to draw those lines.
然后识别直线 并且需要把这些线画出来
And that's what this operation does, is basically finds the lines and then the
这个运算就是要实现这一结果 大致讲来 就是找到这些线
rest is going to draw them, and actually it's going to draw them as segments and,
然后把线画出来 实际效果图是以线段的形式画出来的
with the images, I'm going to illustrate you how we do that.
与原图像一起画出来 我将展示这一点是如何实现的
So let's just run all these operations. and then just see the results.
现在运行代码 看看结果
So, here are the two images. As you see it's pretty fast, and we see
得到这两张图 能看出 运行的速度很快
the original image. This is the accumulator, and here, the
这张图像是原始图像 这是累加器的图
squares, the wide squares are basically the peaks the, basically, the most
这些正方形是峰值所在 或者说是
important maximal in the accumulator. And those are these green lines that we
累加器中最重要的最大值 可以看到这些绿线
see here. Once again in the accumulator, we have
在累加器中 我们能得到ρ和θ
rho and theta. Once we have that we can go back into the
一旦得到这些参数 就可以回到图像平面（也就是x_y平面）中画线
image plain and draw the lines. Now you may wonder, but wait a second,
现在你们可能有疑问 但是稍安勿躁
rho and theta would give us straight lines, but all across the image how do we
ρ 和 θ能得到直线 但是如果我们想得到线段
get to segments if we need to get to segments.
应该如何做呢
And the basic idea is that there are many ways of doing that.
有很多方法可以实现
But one way of doing that is you go and put the line back in the image as we have
其中一个方法是将得到的直线放回到原图中
here. And then you can go around that line and
然后你可以检验这条线
see if there actual points in the image which were detected by the age detector
看看这些点是否就是之前用边缘识别出的为这条直线投票的点
that voted for that line. And you basically can get what actually
基本上通过这种方法 你能得到的是
was the real segment and not the whole line in the image.
真实的线段 而不是一整条线
That's just one way of doing that. And as we see here, we got this straight
这仅是诸多方法中的一种 就像我们看到的 现在得到了这些直线
lines. Very fast, and very simple operation to
整个过程的运算非常快捷且简练
get straight lines. There are others.
非常迅速简单 这是其他线
Just, their votes are weaker, and we need to decide to put a threshold in the
只是其他方法的总票数较少 我们需要为累加器设定阈值
cumulator. We might put a threshold that says don't
可以选择一个阈值 使得少于某一个投票值的直线
give me any line that has less than certain amount of votes,
就不再显示
or we can say give me the ten top lines, give me the, the, the five top lines or
或者是只是让票数排名前十或者前五的直线显示
anything that is application dependent. So with this image and with this example
阈值可根据具体的应用进行调整 在这个例子中
we see the whole pipeline. From the image, detect the edges, create
我们看到了操作的整个流程 从读入图像、识别边缘
the accumulator, find the maximal,
生成累加器 一直到找最值
draw up those lines back to the image. And if you need,
得到这些线后放回原图中进行验证 另外 如果有需要
basically find the segments by looking in the image, where do you have actual
可以在放回原图进行验证时 通过找到图像中为相应直线投过票的点来找到线段
points that voted for that, if you need just the segment.
如果你要找的只是线段
So now we're going to go back and I'm going to describe what we do for circles.
现在我们回过头来 来讲解如何用霍夫变换检测环形
What about circles then? So here we have an image of circles and
环形有什么不同？ 这是一张有很多环形的图片
we are going to know if we can basically find the circle using the half transform.
接下来将要学习能否使用霍夫变换来检测圆边缘
The idea is exactly the same. Now a circle can be written down in the
思路完全相同 一个圆形可以写成如下表达式
following form. X minus X zero, that's a X coordinate of
x－x_0 x_0是圆心在x轴上的坐标
the circle. Square plus Y minus Y zero squared equal
上式的平方 加上y-y_0的平方
to the radius squared so, every point in the circle holds this equation where the
等于圆形半径的平方 圆上所有的点都满足此方程
center of the circle. Is given by this and this.
圆心是x_0 y_0
These are the coordinates of the center, what we need to find.
这是我们需要找到的圆心的坐标
And the radius of the center, which is also an unknown.
同样需要求解的 还有未知的圆的半径
It's given here. If you don't remember this formula, just
这里已经给出公式 如果你们已经忘记了公式
pick any of the elementary geometry books, or just believe me that this
随便找一本基础几何书查找一下 或者是相信我
formula is the right formula for a circle on the plane.
这就是平面上圆的正确表达式
Now in the same way that we need rho and theta for straight lines, we need to find
就像直线的例子中需要找到ρ 和 θ
the center and the radius for a circle. So we need one.
在圆的情况下需要找到圆心和半径 所以现在需要求解3个参数
To three parameters. So now accumu, our accumulator won't be
因此累加器也不再是二维平面的累加器
on the plane. It will be a 3-dimensional accumulator,
而将会是三维空间内的累加器
but we're going to do exactly the same. We're going to have an edge detector.
但是要做的步骤完全一致 首先是边界识别
Every point is not a vote for a circus every point is going to give us.
现在边界识别给出的每个点要为一个环形投票 并且给出自己的坐标
Its coordinates. And then we are going to run through the
然后我们将依次累加圆心的x坐标
accumulator on the X coordinate of the center, the Y coordinate of the center,
累加圆心的y轴坐标
and get the radius. So we are going to run through that,
然后得到半径 也就是我们遍历所有的坐标轴
through the Xs, run through the Ys. And then, get the radius.
先在x轴上累加 再y轴 之后计算半径
We accumulate, we pick the maximum one, and we basically are done.
进行累加 挑出最大值 整个过程就基本完成了
We got our center and radius. So, let us see this straight one example.
这样就得到了圆心和半径 我们通过一个例子对这个过程进行详细说明
Here we have the edges and I want to repeat that once again.
边界信息已经得到 但我想再重复一遍
Every point here will vote for multiple centers, multiple radius.
这里的每一个点可以给多个圆心和半径投票
We can of course limit the centers, because we know the dimensions.
当然 由于事先知道空间维度 我们可以对圆心进行限制
We can also limit the votes for the radius, because we also know how large
我们也可以对半径的投票进行限制 因为我们事先知道
the objects can be in the image. We are going to vote for that.
图像中要识别的对象会有多大 我们将据此进行投票
There are going to be multiple votes for the real circles in the images and then
图像中实际出现的环形会有不同的票数
we basically detect them and here they are.
我们基本已将它们一一识别出来 这是结果
We basically went through that cummulator, and find the top votes.
通过累加 我们可以找到最多的票数
And we get out results. Basically the Hough transform can be used
然后得到结果  一般说来 霍夫变换能够用于
for any parametric curve. Anything that we need to vote for some
能够识别任意能用参数表示出的曲线 需要做的只是对曲线的参数进行投票
parameters of that curve. As rho and theta, the centers we can find
比如ρ 和 θ 再加上焦点 我们可以得到抛物线
parabolas, we can find any, any curve that we can write with parameters.
只要是能用参数描述的曲线 我们都可以找到
The more parameters you have, the more expensive the Hough transform is.
曲线的参数越多 霍夫变换的代价就越大
So normally, the Hough transform is used for finding straights line, circles,
因此 霍夫变换一般用于识别直线 圆和椭圆
ellipses, relatively simple objects that have a
这些参数较少的简单图形
controllable number of parameters. Otherwise, your accumulator space is
否则 累加器的维度会十分庞大
huge, takes a lot of memory, and takes a lot of computational time, both to
占用很多内存和计算时间
compute it and to find the maximal. But for those simple shapes, there's,
不管是计算还是查找最大值 但对于简单图形来说
one of the best techniques out there is the Hough transform.
霍夫变换是最好的技术之一
So I hope you enjoy this video and I'll see you in the next video.
希望你们喜欢这视频 再见
Thank you very much.
非常感谢